this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software this episode of se radio is
brought to you by Braintree if you think
that your payment system exists solely
for the purpose of transferring money
from your customers wallet to yours
think again Braintree rethink payments
learn more at Braintree payments calm /
se radio for Software Engineering radio
this is Jeff Meyerson Philip kren works
at elastic on infrastructure and
developer advocacy he has a degree in
software in information engineering and
has worked for many years as a web
developer prior to joining elastic
Phillip welcome to software engineering
radio hi Geoffrey it's a pleasure to be
here
it's a pleasure to have you most
listeners know what a search engine is
we all use Google to search web pages
but there are many other things that can
be searched through what are some
applications that search is useful for
well pretty much everywhere where you
have lots of information you want to
search for something so elastic search
for example is widely used in lots of
websites and applications one of them
would be Wikipedia so if you search
anything in the search box on Wikipedia
your search will actually go through
elastic search in the background or if
you search on github or Stack Overflow
all of those will actually go through
elastic search in the back end so if you
don't want to rely on your search going
through Google but have it on your own
service or within your own site then you
would need some extra software to
actually do that for you and if we're
talking from a architectural point of
view not from a specific type of search
engine can you describe the high level
components that fit together to allow
users to search through a collection of
data yes so normally I compare it to
relational databases or databases in
general where I would say that databases
are very much black-and-white so you
store something and then you can
retrieve it
whereas full-text search normally
operates more in shades of gray you're
not only interested in exact matches but
you want to have your want to search for
something like a concept so it's more
like shades of grey you don't really
care about if it's singular plural
sometimes you don't even care it if it's
a noun or an adjective you just want to
search for that concept and full-text
search normally adds some overhead in
during the store part so what we call
index you would just index some document
you have and do some additional work for
that before actually storing it too you
can retrieve it afterwards easily so
what that indexing would do is normally
you would remove any formatting like
HTML tags for example then you could
remove something like stop words which
are very common words which appear in
nearly every document and would not add
much value to your documents then you
can do something like stemming which
basically removes the word endings or
reduces a word down to its root so you
don't care about singular plural or any
specific reflection and then you could
also add stuff like synonyms so you have
if you have multiple terms for the same
meaning and you don't know what you
users want to search for you could just
add those synonyms to allow them to
search for any one of them and find the
content you have right you're talking
about the process of building a index to
be searched and the index that we're
searching through is a way to look up
documents so you often have a corpus of
documents the Wikipedia examples perfect
you've got the entirety of Wikipedia
it's all these articles about biology
and physics and history and you want to
be able to map search terms to documents
and in order to do that you build what
is called an inverted index and so you
described it pretty well where
you you're building a way to map search
terms to those different documents so if
I have an article about swimming then it
you know the inverted index will look
through the article about swimming and
it'll find things like water and
chlorine and laps and then if and then
it maps those as the keys in the index
to that article so all of those keys
might map with some degree of accuracy
to that article and how closely they map
to that article is part of the fuzziness
that you're talking about where it's not
like a relational database where you're
always going to get swimming if you look
up the word water but you might get it
sometimes yeah so so what normally
happens for example if we stick to the
the Swimming page on Wikipedia we would
just take that entire document then
extract the top we call them tokens
which is basically all the words you
have there then we run them through this
indexing pipeline we have for example
swimming would probably be reduced down
to swim so if you have swim swimming
that wouldn't make a difference you
would just store the word swim and then
you don't even need fuzziness right away
so as soon as somebody searches for swim
you would have a direct match you could
add fuzziness on top of that so if
somebody would misspelled swim even
though that picked are on that specific
word you could optionally add something
like fuzziness there and of course you
could add synonyms for swim as well if
people want to search for something else
so you're describing these different
ways that you can add richness to what
is the core abstraction of the inverted
index where search terms are mapped to
specific documents that will look we're
looking up and I'm glad that we've been
able to give people an explanation for
this inverted index in case they needed
a reminder or an introduction to it so
with those concepts in mind with that
being the core data structure that we're
building here let's talk about elastic
search what is elastic search
well elasticsearch is one of these
full-text search and the engines it's
based on Apache Lucene that is actually
what is doing all the the hard work we
have just discussed so the scene is the
thing storing the data on disk and
making it searchable it's doing the
indexed process so stop words stemming
tokenization all of that is Lucien's
work and kind of around that like a
shell
we have elastic search and that that
shell or yeah outer layer does the
community SL it provides rest interface
and does the replication and
distribution of you data over multiple
nodes so the actual search work is done
by a petty Lucene and then a nice way to
interact with that that is provided by
elastic search what does the term
elastic refer to well I'm not even
really sure like we started off as
elastic search actually elastic search
was kind of the third implementation the
first two were called compass one and
compass two and then shy our CEO by now
renamed the third one company but he
called the de lastik search and after we
started adding more and more product so
it was not just elastic search anymore I
guess it was just shortened down to
elastic and yeah that's what we have
been sticking to and since elasticity
and scaling and stuff like that is a
common concern I guess the lastik is
very fitting okay yeah that was what I
was hoping it's it indicated because
I've got a lot of questions about
scaling because of course if we're
building a search engine for something
as big as Wikipedia or something as big
as all of the logs that were storing for
our application we're going to need some
elasticity so can you give a
introduction to some of the elastic
properties of this search index that
we're building so there are generally
lots of moving parts so let's start with
kind of the simple stuff in the
background you store your data to one
index the index is pretty much like a
database in the database
and that one index can be split into
multiple so-called shards by default
those would be five shards and each of
these shots can either live on one
server or if you have multiple service
the data would be distributed over your
multiple servers automatically so that
is how we split up data and if you have
more than five servers and want to use
more servers for storage your one index
you would need to change the number of
shots when you create that index and in
addition to that sharding we also
replicate the data so by default we have
a replica of one basically meaning you
have your your five shards and then for
each one of these shots you would have
one copy on another node so if one node
dies and a few shards go missing with
that node you will still have those
replicated on another instance and that
is kind of the basic concept how to
distribute data and also be resilient to
failures and by using that approach it's
very easy to scale horizontally so you
just add more nodes to your cluster and
the shot will be automatically
distributed and replicate it and that's
basically all you need to care for I
think this is a good opportunity to talk
about sharding and replication more
generally because this is a technique
for building a resilient system that is
true whether we're building a search
index or a relational database I know
you just gave a pretty good explanation
for what sharding and replication do but
can you go more generally into what
sharding and replication are just just
maybe give an alternative explanation
for the explanation you just gave so I
think two terms sharding actually
started in in a computer game what it
Ultima Online I cannot recall but there
was a game and there was some crystal
and that crystal was split up into
multiple shards and I think every shard
was one of the game world to something
like that and that is where the term
sharding originally comes from so you
have one big
and you want to divide it into multiple
smaller more manageable pieces and the
example of the crystal yet a crystal was
split up and each one of them contained
some parts of that world where in
anything that stores data the shards
will contain some part of that data you
want to store in its entirety so the
number of shards that we have is a
reflection of how diverse the the volume
of unique pieces of data in our database
and we break up those shards and then we
replicate them some number of times
because first of all the entire the
entire sharded database is too big to
fit on any one machine and second of all
even it you know if that machine if one
of your machines with a unique piece of
data fails then you want to have a
backup so you want to have your shards
replicated on two different machines so
you know we're dealing with these
computer compute environments where
machines are failing all the time you
know for the average user they're
working on AWS and maybe they maybe they
don't notice any failures but if you
work at a company of any reasonable size
you start to notice failures when your
machines you know the machines that
you're spinning up they'll fail
occasionally and so since many of the
biggest companies are hosting their
databases on a cloud service provider
like Amazon Web Services and these
computers are failing all the time it is
important to have a replication factor
which is how many times you're
replicating each piece of data that can
account for how often these machines in
the data center somewhere are failing
what are some strategies around deciding
how often you're going to replicate each
shard of data so maybe we should take
this step back to talk about like why
would you shot like that is one of the
most common questions like how many
shards do you need and what is your
replication factor factor so the thing
about replication is they help with two
things firstly they
make your data more resilient to
failures so depending on how many copies
of your data you have you can take more
numbers of servers that fail but
secondly in the case of elasticsearch
the replicas can also be used to
increase your right Kip you reach
capabilities so you can either read from
one of four from the primary shard or
any of its replicas so if you have some
high-traffic website with for example
you have a shop and black friday comes
along and lots of people want to read
more data from your shop you could just
dynamically increase the number of
replicas to scale up you read since you
have more sources to get your data from
on the other hand to scale up right
you will need more shards so that more
service can spread that writing load
evenly all over all of them and what
further kind of dictates the number of
shots you want to have is either how
much data can one node store so how many
service you really need to store the
data and be what is the write throughput
you want to achieve over all your nodes
so that will kind of dictate your number
of replicas and charts there are no
fixed numbers like often people ask like
what should those numbers be and our
answer is always it depends and one
thing you should definitely avoid is
just thinking well I don't know how many
shots I will use in the future
I will just add a hundred which is
totally a random value but you should
not do that because every shard has a
specific overhead in terms of file
handles and memory and if you have this
rather small cluster and have lots and
lots of shards we always call that over
sharding and you will just lose a lot of
resources just for shining your
deterrent also then if you search over
all your shots you will need to combine
those results from all the shards so
that adds quite some arrowheads it
allows you to scale up very highly but
if you never have that problem to scale
that much you're just wasting lots of
resources on the number of shots so
there is no final answer what is
kind of the right shot or replica number
it will always depend on your use case
also what is your right load what is
your reload and what growth do you
anticipate for the future okay well to
give maybe an idea of at least some
relative charting and replication
factors so Wikipedia is a giant
application and there's tons of users
that are using it and it's also got a
lot of updates it's getting dynamically
updated throughout the day and then
there's also the log management system
for Wikipedia and I imagine that let's
just assume that Wikipedia uses
elasticsearch to manage its logs and I
think we'll get into into log management
with elasticsearch and a little more
detail later on but just as two examples
you know how would you contrast the
scalability the the sharding and the
replication factor of a site like
wikipedia with the log management system
of wikipedia so generally your access
patterns for search and logging are a
bit different so for search normally you
have I would not say small it can be in
the gigabytes or low figures of
terabytes data but your search use case
normally is kind of limited in in the
size of data but you always want to
allow very quick searches on that so
there you will probably have more
service for less data whereas for the
logging use case you often have rather
old data and you do not need queries to
return you that quickly so there you
often have like the limiting factor for
the log use cases often can I ingest all
my know all the data III producing like
if you have I don't know a thousand or
ten thousand updates or requests per
second to store that will dictate how
many notes you need to have and how much
storage do you need depending on how
long you store your data whereas for the
search use case you will have often less
data but it needs to be searchable
really quickly and probably you want to
have lots of memory for
whereas for the storing of log data
often you will have large disks since
it's not that critical if a search takes
like two or three seconds which on the
other hand would be totally inaccessible
for the search use case so it's just a
finding kind of the right trade-off for
the use cases and that will then dictate
what kind of service you need also how
many service you need ok so we jumped to
scalability let's scale back a little
bit and talk about just the core search
index again it probably should have gone
over this more in the beginning but I
think it's ok I think it still fits here
you know we could talk about types and
mappings that you can set up an elastic
search but I think people can look this
information up basically every type
consists of a name and a mapping and so
a blog post for example would have its
own mapping which defines the properties
of of that type that we want index so if
you're if you're indexing your blog with
an elastic search search engine you will
give every blog post a mapping that sets
up some it gives it gives the search
index some information about how you
want results to be returned and this is
sort of like setting up the schema of a
database but this doesn't answer as much
about the fuzziness so let's talk let's
talk a little bit more about like the
fuzziness because as we discussed in the
beginning there is this combination in
in a search engine like a leg elastic
search where you've got part relational
database type of behavior where it's the
the searching that has a clear
definition for what kinds of results
it's going to return and then you have
more of a fuzziness also can you
describe how the relational type of
properties and the fuzziness affect how
how a search query might return results
ok Before we jump into the searching
part one point about the types and the
mapping so firstly mapping
can either be created when you create
the index which you should always do for
production use cases but it would be
Auto automatically generated from the
first document you insert into an index
so if you have some attributes
elasticsearch would try to guess the
right data types from those fields you
provide which is often working
reasonably well for the prototyping
phase but for production you should not
really rely on that and secondly the
types I always say there like an
enumeration type or something like that
on one index you can store different
types of information in one index the
only problem is loosing the underlying
storage engine does not really know
about these types and we have just
decided like one or two weeks ago that
types will in the future go away in
elasticsearch so do not rely on multiple
types in one index too much anymore
because they will be gone in the
perceivable future okay coming back to
the original question about search so
basically what you can do search wise is
we have on the one hand we have
something like boolean queries where you
can define exact things to match so you
could just say this must have a specific
field or this must be in a specific
range and then we have the full search
for text search capabilities which can
work on these index terms so you have
for example you had the stemming from
swimming to swim and it will search on
everything anything that resembles this
swim regardless of it if it was swim
swimming whatever and on top of that you
can put more advanced search concepts
like you could use engrams which would
be like you search for specific groups
of letters in terms if you don't have an
exact match on something that would be
for example if you have blueberry and or
let's say we have blueberries in the
future in the plural and elastic search
for stemming would reduce that to
blueberry with an IIT end but that
wouldn't
imagine anything that is blue to search
for something like that
you would need to extract groups of
letters to actually be able to match
that blue since we do not do any partial
matches otherwise otherwise we would
just compare the entire token do we have
or another advanced search context would
be we can add this fuzziness so we can
say a few letters are either missing
different or too much between what we
have stored and what you're searching
basically this is a levenshtein distance
so with the Levenstein distance of one
for example you could have a word in
your index and what you search for if
that has one letter too little one
letter different or one letter too much
that would still match and in the
beginning we implemented it quite
naively with a brute-force approach but
it has been then we implemented with
full automaton to actually be able to
generate kind of a network of all the
possibilities to not rely on the
brute-force approach of fuzziness so
that should make it much quicker to
search for stuff or things like that
ok now that we've talked about the setup
of our indexing and we've talked about
the elasticity components let's talk
about a read from top to bottom so let's
say I open up Wikipedia I do a search
for how to how to learn to swim let's
say that what's gonna happen on the
server side when that query hits the
elastic search cluster right so we have
the clients for different languages so
we have the bindings for whatever your
language might be Python Ruby Java nuts
and lots of others so you would probably
use that binding or you could just fire
a rest request against any of the nodes
you have a new cluster and normally we
will run Robin between the nodes you
have configured in your connection so
you pick one of these nodes by randomly
since your round robin
and that node will be your client node
previously we caught that coordinating
node as well and that will coordinate
your query so you sent a request to that
one node that node temp figures out okay
this is the specific index the index has
these sharks and replicas and it will
make sure that your query hits every
single shot either primary or replica
and hit the right notes where these
shots resign
yeah where wherever they they live and
then each node having one of these
sharks would actually do your search on
that node and get the partial result of
that node and then it would send that
partial result back to the coordinating
node and that node would then put
together the the entire result actually
it's even a bit more complicated than
that
in the first step all the shards would
only return kind of their matches so if
you search for the 10 best hits each of
these shards would return it's on 10
best matches but only the ID and the
so-called squirrel with score which is
basically a quality attribute the
coordinating node would then take the 10
best results globally from all this up
results it has and would request the
documents the nodes having the data or
have by just requesting them through the
ID has received so it says two-step
approach it's like a scatter gather
where you just get the IDS first and
then collect the final results and then
the coordinating node will send you back
that result that you have just requested
ok in that example you talked about the
client or coordinator node is this any
node in the cluster are all of the nodes
potentially client nodes so by default
it could be any node but you can split
up the roles of the elasticsearch nodes
so we have data nodes these keep data
and 2d actuals
we have master notes these keep track of
the status of the entire cluster we have
client nodes these don't keep any data
themselves they are just coordinating
these queries and requesting the results
quite freshly in the latest five five
release we have so-called ingest nodes
which can do some processing and
enrichment of the data when you store it
and we also have tribe nodes which can
connect to multiple clusters and by
default I know it would be a master node
and a data node and would just do all
the work but once you have a bigger and
bigger cluster you might want to split
up these different roles of nodes to
specify them a bit more and to keep your
cluster in a more reliable state so you
would start out by splitting out the
master nodes so that they just keep the
state of the cluster in turn to any
other hard work so to keep your cluster
state quite reliable and then you could
also split out these client nodes for
example if you do very big aggregates
that takes up a lot of memory and you do
not want to your data nodes to swap out
all the data they have just fetched from
disk to memory because they need to put
together some big aggregate you wouldn't
want to pay that price to always refetch
data from the disk just because some
other process just took up all your
memory and expired the cache you had so
you would split that up so your data
nodes just have as much data loaded into
memory as possible whereas the client
nodes they are good for coordinating
your queries and then combining results
together to the final set you want to
return to your application this podcast
is supported by atlanticnet hosting
solution provider of healthcare HIPAA
PCI compliance and AdTech if you're
feeling the pain of having outdated
technology call atlanticnet and get the
latest security firewall intrusion
detection backup disaster recovery and
virtualization or if you're starting a
new project or not giving the results
you want from your car
providers atlanticnet can help you
succeed
the fully audited solutions in 23 years
in business they won't let you down
visit atlanticnet to learn more as i
mentioned earlier these elasticsearch
clusters are often in a data center
somewhere with dubious hardware quality
on some of the machines and nodes are
failing all the time so you may have a
failure in the middle of a query you may
have the failure a failure in the middle
of a right actually before we talk about
those failures we just discussed a read
why don't you discuss a right okay so a
right it will depend do you provide the
ad yourself or do you let elasticsearch
generate dat in any case any document
you have will have an ID either assigned
by you or generated by elasticsearch
then the next step is whatever the
client node is it will hash that ID so
it will be evenly distributed over all
the shards and then after hashing the ID
it knows which the right primary shot
for that data is that is part of the
cluster state information so it knows
this area of the hash value is for that
shot and that shard resides on that
specific node so it will forward the
data to the primary shard where that ID
landed on after being hashed and then
the primary shot will check is this a
meaningful document can I insert it does
that not conflict with the mapping I
have so for example if you have a field
and values of the type integer and you
would you try to insert a string there
the node would immediately see well I
cannot process that and would give you
back a client error but assume
everything works and you can apply the
document to that specific index and type
it would write that data down in we call
it trans login phosphorus it would be
like okay write a head lock so that data
would be written down
and then it would be forwarded to the
replicas like my default one you could
set it to zero or more than one these
would then accept write write it down as
well and only then would the primary
shot acknowledge to write back to the
client note and would then let it know
okay I have applied that right operation
all done so it would return 201 if it
had created the document or a 200 if it
had just updated the document
one thing that is might be a bit
surprising is that data if you do a
full-text search in it is not
immediately available by default so by
default we have something called a
refresh so of one second so every second
all the documents you have added would
be added to this inverted index actually
the scene would create a new segment for
each of these one-second intervals you
have and that is what is then stored on
this scan world is actually searchable
you can immediately retrieve a document
by its ID but it's only available
through the full-text search part after
this refresh interval has passed and
that again is a trade-off of performance
so you could either set this much higher
then you would write fewer segments but
it takes longer until your documents are
searchable all you can keep a lower
value like one second or you could even
disable it entirely but then you would
have lots of very small documents which
will probably not perform that well but
the documents are very quickly
searchable then so again it depends on
how quickly you want to be able to
search something we've talked through
both the read and the write processes
now both of them involve a lot of
coordination so what happens during a
machine failure in one of these it well
maybe you could describe some failure
cases of Reed and feather cases of right
you don't have to go and I guess that's
a big question but take it for what you
will
well so depending on what kind of
machine fails different things will
happen if it was just a note keeping
data at some point the other nose nodes
will recognize that there's a specific
time out how long do we wait until the
assumed the note is really dead and once
they that they know this mark does that
in a cluster stand the master node will
make sure that the data is replicated in
the right fashion again so the note that
has died if it had any primary shots and
you have any replica shots of those
those replica shots would be marked as
primary shots then on another note and
those charts would then be replicated to
another note to again get to your
replica factor you have configured and
if some replica shots are on the server
and they're gone the primary shot would
make sure that it replicates it's dated
to another note if your master node
fails they can always be one master node
in your elasticsearch cluster since that
is the one instance that keeps track of
your cluster state the other master
eligible notes would do a vote on who
can become the next master and who keeps
them track of that master state so this
is kind of what happens when a node dies
and then if the read or write operation
goes out and it's just a failure is in
flight the operation would then just
timeout is there is timeout for every
query when there is an error just
happening at that specific moment but as
soon as we have something reachable
again the coordinating node would direct
the traffic to the right node okay well
I have heard about these issues where if
you're somebody who is managing an
elasticsearch cluster there are these
statuses I guess like a read at yellow
and a green status that indicate how
live a node on a cluster is and if you
have things that are
in a yellow state this is equivalent to
the canonical partial failure and
partial failures in computer science are
typically harder to deal with than
complete failures can you talk about
what causes partial failures and why
those are so hard to manage in an
elastic search cluster so the the colors
you mentioned like green studies you
have all the primary shots you have are
available and all the replicas you have
configured are also available in your
cluster the yellow state means you have
all your primary shots so there is at
least one copy of the data but your
replication Factory is not honored at
the moment so if you have a replication
factor of 1 and no dies and your
replicas or your primary is gone you
still have the data copy so you have one
copy all your data is readable and
writeable at that moment but you do not
honor your replication factor and while
the data is being replicated to another
node you will be stuck on that yellow
state also if you have just a single
node and you have a replication factor
of 1 it cannot replicate to that node it
doesn't make sense to replicate data on
the same node 2 we will never do that
and the data always needs to be
replicated to another node so if you
have a replication factor one with a
single node that cluster will always be
in the yellow state so all your queries
will work but you do not have the kind
of the capabilities to have all the
copies you want so you're not as
resilient as you could be and only the
red state means that some data is not
available so for example if you have a
repetitive replication factor of zero
and a node with that one copy of the
data failed your index would be in the
or your cluster would be in the red
state or if you have a replication
factor of 1 and 2 nodes fail and one of
them has the primary shot and the other
one has the replica shot for that
specific cluster then your cluster would
be in a red state so not all your data
is available anymore
that is basically what these colors mean
okay well so we've explored many of the
scalability aspects of elastic search
we've explored the basic data structure
that we are scaling which is the
inverted index let's talk about some
application level architectural level
questions the typical application these
days uses multiple different databases
to store its data and this is the
polyglot persistence model in something
even in something like Wikipedia where
you've been discussing elastic search as
the main system of record I imagine if I
click on a link for a page sometimes
things within that page are going to
have to load data from a database and
it's probably pulling from a place that
is not elastic search because it
wouldn't make sense if the if the query
to get the page the page assets is very
well defined you wouldn't want to go to
an elastic search cluster I assume but
please tell me if I'm wrong so if I'm if
I remember correctly PDA is using
MariaDB for the story top of its data
and then for full text search would add
elastic search something like that is a
very common scenario yeah okay can you
talk more generally about polyglot
persistence and how elastic search fits
into a multi database model so I think
like polyglot persistence was very
appealing in the beginning or
specifically for developers but for the
ops people polyglot off means quite a
headache because when you develop on
some feature for two weeks that is fine
for you but if jobs people have then to
maintain it for the next three years
they're probably less happy if you just
add random data stores so while I think
that using multiple data stores makes
perfect sense I think you should be kind
of careful not to add too many just to
experiment with stuff since your Ops
people will not be too happy with you in
long long term
so there aren't these examples where you
have like five data stores for one thing
and I'm never sure if that is really a
good idea but of course you can do that
so one common aspect where elasticsearch
would come into the picture is if you
need some good and scalable full-text
search capabilities for your product
which is often an important point for I
don't know shop systems big
informational sites and another point
where elastic search comes in handy is
if you have any locks you want to store
and then be able to search them or if
you have anything around metrics
analytics those are our use cases where
elastic search often fits well and it
can cover quite a lot of ground for that
and there's always this loose if
question like is elastic search good
primary data store and normally our
answer is it's not really a primary data
store some people use it as such but
we're not sure it's always the right fit
rate like it always depends sometimes it
can work but for many use cases you
don't want to put all your eggs in one
basket and have it in the full-text
search ends engine especially for
resiliency reasons while we're improving
a lot they're always like smaller issues
you can run into and so it's always a
trade-off between ease-of-use
powerfulness resiliency and for
relational databases for example they
had I would say like 30 years kind of to
bake and know of the no sequel solutions
has had any time close to that to evolve
and mature so yes often a conservative
approach for that is probably still a
good approach and even though I work for
elastic I would not say just use elastic
search for everything
be careful use it for the right
approaches or problems to solve and then
it will make you very happy but it's not
the hammer and nail thing you just use
one tool for everything that's probably
still not a great idea
so yeah polyglot definitely has a place
but just be careful like not to have an
explosion of data storage technologies
like probably for many people something
like ulation
database will work well maybe a
key-value store for caching and keeping
session information and then elastic
search for full-text search logging
metrics but it will always depends the
nice thing is there is so much
technology around that you can just
explore but it also makes it much harder
to find the right combination of tools I
guess so if your Wikipedia and you're
using elastic search and you're also
using Maria DB is Maria DB like a full
representation of your war of the same
elastic search world or does the elastic
search cluster or does this does the
does the single point of truth have to
be replicated elsewhere
like I guess my question is is Maria DB
here in this architecture that we're
discussing and we're not talking the
exact architecture of Wikipedia but
maybe a hypothetical architecture the
Wikipedia might resemble are we writing
to Maria or are we are we keeping Maria
DB which is a relational database are we
keeping that because the query shapes
that will hit that database are
different than elastic search or are we
keeping it because it's a backup a
reliable backup that we can use in place
of elastic search so what I'm not sure
of the specific architecture of
Wikipedia I don't think it's it's a
backup like I'm not sure that is that is
the general use case people want to do
while SQL can be a bit hard and daunting
at some points like it's still very
powerful and widely used so many
developers also want to use that so I
don't think you would add a relational
database just as a backup but you will
often interact with that directly
whereas you would then just offload the
search capabilities to elastic search
and probably logging in metrics and
other use cases so let's talk a little
bit more about the logging example we
touched on it a little bit earlier but
elastic search is widely used as a
system of record for logging and I think
there are a number of reasons
for this one I can think of is that you
know you the the log data is there's so
much log data a lot of it is well-formed
like you have your log messages that are
well-formed until you can make a recent
a decent schema out of it using the
elasticsearch models for doing scheme of
the mappings and the types but also you
can afford to lose some log data I think
so so it's not catastrophic if you're
you know if you end up having this this
type of failure that you're talking
about like why don't you use why
wouldn't you use elasticsearch as the
core system of record maybe it's okay to
lose some data for logging but I
shouldn't talk so much about this so
maybe you could just speak a little bit
about the typical logging infrastructure
that somebody is using when they're
using elasticsearch yeah so first of I
like I am just careful not to give the
wrong impression here but it's not like
if you use elasticsearch that you will
just lose documents every day okay like
this is not what is happening like even
if you're testing stuff on the lab
conditions and you just crashing notes
all the time losing data is actually
quite hard and takes some effort to do
and if as long as you have configured
your cluster and you're using an
up-to-date version since we're improving
quite a lot on resiliency as well like
data loss is not something you will
experience commonly like most people who
lose state or pretty much everybody or
all the cases I've seen for the last
half year or so or even longer we're
mostly like bad configurations and yeah
there's probably nothing to do against
that but like data loss is not something
that happens very commonly okay coming
back to your original question I think
what was also the appeal of
elasticsearch is that it has more of
this entire stack around it because at
first when you think about it full text
search and log management don't really
go together that well or it just sounds
like two different problems to solve the
nice thing about elastic search and the
so called elastic stack is that it's
kind of an entire ecosystem around that
so we have log stash to parse an
enriched data and in the beginning it
would also collect
logs now we have the beats which will
which a lot just like lightweight H into
shippers you can run on all your service
they will just forward data and can
either insert the data directly into
elasticsearch or having the parsed and
enriched by locks - enriching would be
something like you have an IP address
and you want to get the geolocation of
that IP address so you would just store
the city the country and the region of
that IP address you can easily pinpoint
that afterwards and once you have
everything in elasticsearch you can then
use Cabana to visualize and explore your
data so with these four open-source
products you cannot have an total stack
to monitor your metrics and logs and I
guess that is one of the big appeals and
on the other hand since it's open source
it's very easy and cheap to get started
and thanks to the horizontal scalability
of elasticsearch it's also very easy to
scale it up so we have customers using
dozens or of nodes in one cluster or
even three digit notes in one cluster
just to store lots and lots of these
logs you have so we're running low on
time but just one more question as it as
an application perspective because I
think we've we've touched on a lot of
the lower level details what if I was
building a ride-sharing platform and I
wanted to search a geo space to find the
nearest cars to a user my understanding
is that elastic search would be useful
for this can you explain why that is oh
yeah we have we call him geo Nick so in
in earlier versions of the Petula scene
you could do queries so you have a
longitude and latitude you have a point
and then you can either just calculate
the distance or to a specific
geometrical figure around it and find
stuff within a region so there were lots
of capabilities but performance was not
that great
and that elastic people figured out that
that was not or that was an issue at
some point and then they hired one of my
new colleagues
Nick nice we call him a eunuch and he
really meant the Geo features on the
scene and once they were in the scene we
could add them to elasticsearch and now
geo locations are very useful in
elasticsearch and also very performant
especially since version 5 since they
were pretty much totally rewritten there
so geolocation is just having a point
and then finding another close point or
finding all the points in one region
that is totally doable like in the Cure
a DSL we have quite powerful community
geo query capabilities what are some of
the features that are being worked on
within elasticsearch right now it's so
many that is kind of hard to keep track
at the moment so big stuff coming in the
next versions is again on the resiliency
side we're adding sequence numbers which
should help with speeding up the
replications in case of failures and
also at some point lying cross
datacenter replication so you cannot
only have a cluster in one location like
one AWS region but could probably
replicate the data over to another
cluster in another location we will get
rid of types we are always trying to
improve the upgrade process so right now
the upgrade process of elastic search
between major versions is a cluster
restart which is for many people very
painful we're also working on lots of
performance improvements both on the
loose inside and in elastic search
itself and the entire stack is kind of
moving so in all of the open source and
those are commercial plugins there are
lots of new stuff coming up
we've just had elastic on our yearly
conference in San Francisco and there we
already kind of got previews of some of
the cool new features coming up so kind
of my personal favourites are for file
beat the thing that collects log files
it will automatically support
specific protocols now which makes it
much easier to get started so you can
just collect something like syslog nginx
logs Apache logs those will be
automatically parsed in the right format
so it will extract something like HTTP
headers or return codes IP addresses geo
locations and store that in
elasticsearch and you don't need to
configure anything hosszú Cubana is
getting lots of new visualizations and a
way to to visually build metric metrics
or to visualize your metrics easier
elasticsearch is improving on that
upgrade process and also adding yeah
more advanced features I don't want to
dive too deep into right now log stash
is getting it's persistent queue
mechanisms so that you probably don't
need a queue in front of it anymore
which was a common use case so these
persistent queues are in the works and
we're also improving the monitoring
aspect of all the components so right
now we monitor elasticsearch Cubana and
log stash beat will be added soon and in
one of the upcoming versions we will
also collect logs elasticsearch for
example produces in elasticsearch itself
again so you can search those easily but
you probably want to throw that into a
second cluster but just to grow the
stack right now it's pretty much blocks
of Legos so you have all these elements
but there's some assembly required to
put them together and I think that the
next steps are to make this starting
experience nicer so there are more
features or more solutions coming right
out of the box and less assembly for our
users required even though you will
still be able to kind of configure
anything you want you're free to do
whatever you use cases it can be logging
search analytics metrics the elastic
sector is not a one-trick pony just
focused on one of them but we're always
trying to expand to to new horizons for
example we've recently acquired a
machine learning company and machine
learning basically anomaly detection
that is one of the big things that will
come out very soon
so where can people find you on line
either social media or otherwise yes so
I should be very easy to find once you
know my online nickname which is Sierra
which sounds very weird and many people
think it must be something like Xena and
I'm a girl but no it's not it's actually
rot13 of my last name which is crane
Kaori mm and when you rotate these
letters by 13 it's X II are double a
that is both my Twitter handle you can
find me at 0 dot net on the interwebs
and I'm pretty much wherever I am I use
that nickname because nobody else does
so once you have that I should really
defined and I'm doing lots and lots of
conferences and meetups mainly in Europe
so you will have a good chance to find
me I think until summer I have already
20 conference scheduled now so yeah I
will be around if you're in Europe
you should be easy but it should be easy
to find me and I'm always happy to hand
out stickers and answer questions there
alright well I hope you come to the
States for an American tour sometime
soon as well
yeah and I'm currently discussing with
our marketing team if we if we could do
that let's see ok ok I will fill up
thanks a lot for coming on software
engineering radio oh it was all my
pleasure thank you thanks for listening
to se radio an educational program
brought to you by Triple E software
magazine for more about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website at SE - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at se radio.com you can also
email us at team @ SC - radio net this
and all other episodes of se radio is
licensed under Creative Commons license
2.5
thanks for listening